I'm now going to talk for a bit about models.
이제 모델에 대해 비트 좀 할게요
A term you often hear is the term frontier models, which refers to the llms that are pioneering what
프런티어 모델이라는 용어가 종종 등장하는데 오늘날 가능한 가장 큰 모델을
is possible today, the largest possible models.
개척하는 llms를 뜻하죠
And often when people say frontier models, they're referring to the closed source models, the paid
사람들이 개척자 모델이라고 할 때 주로 비공개 소스 모델을 말합니다 GPT나
models like GPT and Claude.
클로드 같은 유료 모델이죠
Actually, sometimes people also say frontier models when they're referring to the biggest, strongest
사실, 프런티어 모델이라고 하는 사람들도 있어요 가장 크고 강력한 오픈
open source models as well.
소스 모델을 언급할 때요
So depending on the context, it could mean either thing.
문맥에 따라 둘 다 될 수 있어요
But let's first talk about the closed source frontier models.
먼저 비공개 프런티어 모델에 대해 얘기해 보죠
And these are also sometimes called the super scalers.
슈퍼 스케일러라고도 불리죠
They are the largest, highest scale of the models.
가장 크고 높은 모형이죠
So first of all, the one that needs no introduction I'm sure is GPT from OpenAI.
먼저, 오픈AI의 GPT는 설명이 필요 없겠죠?
When ChatGPT came out in late 2022, it caught us all off guard with its power.
2022년 말 챗GPT가 나왔을 때 그 출력에 다들 깜짝 놀랐어요
And I'm sure you're familiar with it.
당신도 잘 알 거예요
Claude from anthropic.
인류학의 클로드예요
Anthropic is the competitor to OpenAI.
앤트로픽은 오픈라이의 경쟁자죠
That's that's very well known.
잘 알려진 사실이죠
And Claude is the one that's that's usually favored by data scientists.
데이터 과학자들이 좋아하는 건 클로드예요
but Claude and GPT are often considered neck and neck right now in the leaderboards.
클로드와 GPT는 현재 순위표에서 막상막하로 평가받죠
Claude has the slight edge.
클로드는 살짝 더 날카롭죠
Gemini is Google's entrant.
제미니는 구글의 참가자죠
You probably remember from when we looked at llama that they also Google also has Gemma.
라마를 검색했을 때 기억하실 거예요 구글에도 제마가 있어요
The the open source variant as well.
오픈 소스 변종도요
And command R is one that you may or may not have come across from cohere.
명령 R은 코어에서 접할 수도 있고 아닐 수도 있어요
Canadian AI company.
캐나다 인공지능 회사요
And then perplexity is a search engine which actually can use one of the other models, but also has
당황스러움은 검색 엔진으로 다른 모델을 사용할 수 있지만 모델 그 자체도
a model itself.
있어요
So these are some of the big frontier models.
이건 개척 시대의 대형 모델이에요
And let's talk about some of the open source models.
오픈 소스 모델에 대해 얘기해보죠
So llama uh, after which llama is named llama from meta is of course the most famous of the open source
라마는 메타에서 따온 이름인데 오픈 소스 모델 중 가장 유명하죠 메타가 원조 라마를
models because meta paved the way in the field of open source LMS by open sourcing the original llama
오픈 소스 소스 오픈 소싱해 오픈 소스 LMS 영역의 길을 포장한 거니까요
Uh, there's one called Mistral from, uh, French company Mistral, which is a model, which is what
프랑스 회사 미스트랄의 미스트랄도 있는데 모델명이에요 전문가들을
they call a mixture of experts.
섞은 거죠
It contains multiple smaller models.
작은 모델도 여러 개 포함돼 있죠
Quen is a model that I mentioned back when we were playing with Obama.
퀜은 오바마와 경기할 때 제가 언급했던 모델이에요
It is a powerhouse model.
강력한 모델이죠
It's really super impressive from Alibaba Cloud, and we will use Quan from time to time because it's
알리바바 클라우드에서 나온 건데 정말 인상적이에요 콴을 가끔 사용할 거예요 말씀드렸듯이
it's as I say, it's very powerful for its size.
크기에 비해 아주 강력하거든요
Gemma I mentioned is Google's smaller model and Fi is Microsoft's smaller open source model.
젬마는 구글의 작은 모델이고 Fi는 마이크로소프트의 작은 오픈 소스 모델이죠
So this is confusing and it's super important.
헷갈리지만 아주 중요해요
And it's something which some of you may already know, but but it might be something that's been nagging
이미 아는 분들도 있겠지만 몇몇 분들은 계속 마음에
as well at a few of you.
걸렸을 거예요
And I want to be really clear on this.
확실히 해두고 싶어요
There are different ways that you can use models that are in completely different approaches, and it's
완전히 다른 접근법으로 모델을 사용할 수 있는 다양한 방법이 있어요 그 둘의 차이를
important to understand the differences between them and when you come across them, being used in those
이해하는 게 중요하죠 마주쳤을 때 다른 방식으로 사용될 수도
different ways.
있고요
Have in your mind what's going on here.
무슨 일인지 잘 생각해 봐요
So first of all, there are chat interfaces to using models, obviously like ChatGPT, which is a web
먼저 모델을 이용한 채팅 인터페이스가 있습니다 챗GPT 같은 거죠 채팅하는 웹 프런트엔드로서
front end where you are chatting and you are calling something that's running in the cloud, and that
클라우드에서 실행 중인 뭔가를 호출하는 겁니다 LLM LM과의 상호 작용
the whole process of interacting with the LLM LM is being handled by OpenAI on their cloud.
전 과정은 그들의 클라우드에서 OpenAI가 처리하고요
In the case of ChatGPT, there's also, of course, a Cloud and Gemini Advance and others.
챗GPT의 경우 클라우드와 제미니 어드밴스 등의 제약 회사가 있죠
There are cloud APIs.
클라우드 API가 있어요
And this is where again, you are calling something that's running on the cloud, but you're doing it
여기서 클라우드에서 실행되는 걸 호출하지만 사용자 인터페이스가
with code, not through a user interface.
아니라 코드로 하죠
And what we did in the summarization Jupyter notebook, Jupyter Lab was calling OpenAI's API.
요약본에 있는 유피터 노트북에서 유피터 랩은 OpenAI API라고 명명했죠
We were connecting to OpenAI, calling their API, and with the chat interfaces you typically it's it's
OpenAI에 연결해서 API 호출을 하고 채팅 인터페이스를 이용하면 무료로
either free for a free tier, or you're paying a monthly subscription fee to use the user interface
사용할 수 있고 매달 사용료를 내야 사용자 인터페이스 채팅을 원하는 만큼
chat almost as much as you want.
사용할 수 있어요
There are some limits there.
거기에도 한계가 있어요
It's different with the APIs.
API는 달라요
With the APIs, there's no subscription, there's no monthly charge, but rather you pay for every API
API는 구독이 없어요 매달 돈을 청구하지 않죠 대신 API 요청에 대한 비용을
request you make.
지불해요
If it's a paid API.
유료 API 경우에요
There are also open source free APIs too, so you can call the APIs directly.
오픈 소스 무료 API도 있어요 API를 직접 호출할 수 있죠
There are also libraries like Lang Chain, which give you a kind of abstraction layer, and you can
랭 체인 같은 라이브러리도 있어요 일종의 추상 레이어를 제공하죠 랭 체인을 사용할
use Lang chain.
수 있어요
And then within it you can call the different APIs.
그 안에서 다양한 API를 호출할 수 있어요
And it presents you with one API that is unified across them.
통합된 API 하나를 제공하죠
And so there are some of these frameworks like Lang chain.
랑 체인 같은 틀이 있어요
And if you see someone using Lang chain, it's really just using the lm API under the covers.
랭 체인을 사용하는 사람을 보면 커버 아래 lm API만을 사용하죠
It's just giving you a nicer user, nicer API interface, more consistent, uh, on top of it.
더 나은 사용자와 API 인터페이스를 제공할 뿐이죠 더 일관성 있는 거요
And then there's another type of API which is a bit of a different take, which is using something called
또 다른 API 유형은 약간 다른데요 관리되는 인공 지능 클라우드 서비스라는
a managed AI cloud service, which is where you are connecting with a provider like Amazon, Google
걸 사용합니다 아마존, 구글 또는 마이크로소프트 Azure 같은 공급자와 연결하는 거죠 비트로소프트
or Microsoft Azure.
클라우드 서비스
And they are running the models on their cloud, and they're presenting you with a common interface
클라우드에서 모델을 실행하고 공통 인터페이스를 제공해 여러분이 뒤에서
so that you can run behind the scenes.
실행할 수 있게 하죠
It could be open source, it could be closed source.
오픈 소스일 수도 있고 폐쇄 소스일 수도 있죠
And you'll hear of Amazon Bedrock.
아마존 베드록도 있어요
That's Amazon's offering.
아마존이 제공하는 거죠
Google vertex AI is Google's and Azure ML.
구글의 정점 인공지능은 구글과 애저 ML이죠
It goes by some other names too is Microsoft's offering.
다른 이름도 있어요 마이크로소프트가 제공하죠
So these are the managed AI cloud services.
관리되는 인공지능 클라우드 서비스죠
But what all of these have in common is that you are writing code Locally.
하지만 이 모든 것의 공통점은 로컬에서 코드를 작성한다는 거죠
That then makes a call to an LM running in the cloud, and that is the cloud API.
클라우드에서 실행되는 LM에 호출을 하는데 그게 클라우드 API예요
And then there's a third approach, and that is when you get the code and the weights for an LM yourself
세 번째 접근법은 LM에 대한 코드와 무게를 직접 알아내서 여러분의
and you run it yourself, uh, on your box or potentially by remoting into a remote box.
박스에서 실행하거나 원격 get box로 원격 조종하는 것이죠.
And here again, there's two different ways that we will be doing it on this course.
다시 말씀드리지만 이 코스에서는 두 가지 다른 방법이 있어요
And it's important to understand the differences between them.
그 둘의 차이를 이해하는 게 중요해요
One of them is using hugging face, where we will be able to get access to like the Python code and
하나는 얼굴 안기입니다 파이썬 코드와 해당 모델이 있는 PyTorch
the PyTorch code, which has that model in it.
코드에 엑세스할 수 있죠
And we'll be able to then work in a fairly granular way with that model, will be able to use it to
이 모델을 가지고 세분화 작업을 할 수 있습니다. 토큰화 텍스트 같은 작업을
do things like tokenized text, and then call the model with the tokens, and you'll be actually operating
할 수 있고 토큰으로 모델을 호출할 수 있습니다. 실제로 모델을 운영할 수 있죠.
And we'll typically do that using something like Google Colab, where we can be running it on a very
일반적으로 구글 Colab 같은 걸 사용합니다 클라우드 내
high powered box in the cloud, because typically one's local box isn't powerful enough to run that
고성능 상자에서 실행할 수 있죠 일반적으로 로컬 상자는 그런 수준의 프로세싱을
kind of, uh, that level of processing.
실행할 만큼 강력하지 않거든요
And as an alternative to that, people have taken this code and they've optimized it into high performance
그 대신 사람들은 이 코드를 고성능 C++ 코드로 최적화해 컴파일했고
C plus plus code and compiled it so that you can run it locally on your box.
여러분의 박스에서 로컬로 실행할 수 있게 됐죠
And that is what Olama is.
그게 올라마예요
It uses something called llama CPW behind the scenes as the C plus plus code.
llama CPW라는 걸 사용합니다 C 플러스 코드로요
Now that means that you can run it locally.
그 말은 로컬로 실행할 수 있다는 거죠
You're running the models in inference and execution mode on your box, but you don't have as much ability
추론과 실행 모드로 모델을 실행하고 있지만 무슨 일이 일어나는지 제어할 능력은
to control what's going on because it's just fully compiled code.
별로 없어요 코드가 완전히 컴파일됐으니까요
So that gives you hopefully some insight.
그게 도움이 됐으면 좋겠네요
I'm glossing over some of the details, but hopefully shows you the landscape of the three different
세부 사항은 대충 말씀드렸지만 여러분께 보여드릴 수 있길 바라요 모델을
ways that you can work with models, and then some of the sort of sub sub techniques under that.
다루는 세 가지 다른 방법과 그 밑에 있는 일종의 서브 테크닉을요
With all of that, what are we going to do now?
이제 어떻게 할 거예요?
We're going to do an exercise, and it's going to be a useful exercise, and one that you'll be able
오늘 할 운동은 아주 유용할 겁니다 수업 내내 계속
to continue using throughout the course, because it's going to involve olama.
활용할 수 있죠 올라마를 배울 거니까요
And without further ado, I'm going to flip over to JupyterLab to explain the exercise.
그럼 지체 없이 유피터랩으로 넘어가서 이 운동에 대해 설명하죠